a 0.25 kilogram ball
attached to a 1.5 meter rope
moves at a constant speed of 15 meters
per second around a vertical circle
calculate the tension force on the rope
at the bottom i mean at the top bottom
and at the middle of the circle
now let's distinguish horizontal
circular motion
from vertical circular motion
so here's horizontal circular motion
and the tension force
is approximately equal
to the centripetal force it's mv squared
over r
and
this is especially true if the ball is
moving fast enough if it's not
it's going to be at an angle
and the circle is going to be nearly
horizontal
let me draw a better circle than that
if it's not moving fast enough you need
to
incorporate the fact that we have t y
and t x
and this is t
and you have the weight force mg
so to calculate the tension force
it's going to be
the square root of t x squared plus t y
square
and t x provides the centripetal force
that's the horizontal part so t x is mv
squared over r
t y
supports the weight of the ball
so t y is going to be mg
if the ball is moving fast enough
t y is going to be relatively small to t
x so
you can approximate t just using this
equation
if it's not moving fast enough if it's
moving slow then you have to use this to
calculate the tension force
now that's for a horizontal circle
but what about a vertical circle
how can we calculate the tension force
at point a
b
and c
here's a question for you
let's say if you have a rope and a ball
attached to it
and imagine swinging it in the vertical
circle
will it feel heaviest at point a b or c
if you notice the ball will feel heavier
at point c
because not only do you need to support
the weight of the ball
but you have to lift it up to get to it
to get to point b if you're moving in
this direction
it turns out that the tension force at
point c
is the sum of the weight force
and the centripetal force
at point a is the difference
of the centripetal force
and the weight force
at point b if it's moving fast enough
the tension force is approximately equal
to
the centripetal force
if it's not moving fast enough
let's see if i can put it here
this is also the same as point d as well
and point b if it's not moving fast
enough it's going to be the square root
of mv squared over r
squared that's tx squared
plus
mg squared which is t y squared
so that's how you can find the exact
tension force at points b and d
but for the most part if it's moving
fast enough you can approximate it
to mv squared over r this will become
insignificant
now let's talk about how to derive those
equations before we actually
work out this problem
so at the top of the circle
we have a downward tension force
and also
a downward weight force
so the sum of all the forces in the y
direction
is going to be negative t because t is
going in the negative y direction
and negative mg
now based on newton's second law the net
force is equal to ma
now the net force is also
in the negative y direction so i'm going
to put negative ma
and the acceleration
that points towards the center of the
circle
that is the centripetal acceleration so
and the centripetal acceleration
is v squared
over r
so therefore what we have here is the
centripetal force
and that's equal to negative t minus mg
now our goal is to calculate the tangent
force at the top
so i'm going to take this term move it
to the left side to make it positive
and then take this term move it to the
right side to make that positive so on
the left i'm going to have positive t
is equal to positive mv squared over r
on the right minus mg
so the tension force at the top at point
a
is the difference
between the centripetal force mv squared
over r and the weight force mg
so now let's go ahead and calculate it
so it's going to be 0.25
times 15 squared
divided by 1.5
minus 0.25
times 9.8
so the tension force at the top
is about 35 newtons
so now let's calculate it at the bottom
so at the bottom of the circle
we have an upward tangent force
and we have a downward
weight force
so the net force in the y direction
is equal to the upward tension force
it's positive because
it's pointing in a positive y direction
mg is negative because it still points
in a negative y direction
now the centripetal acceleration is
upward which means that the net force is
also upward
so we're going to replace this with
positive
m a
and so that's going to be t
minus mg
and a is v squared over r
so i'm going to take this term and move
it to this side
so i'm going to have mv squared over r
plus mg
and that's equal to the tension force
so at the bottom of the circle the
tension force is the sum
of the centripetal force and the weight
force
so this is going to be 0.25 times 15
squared
divided by the radius of 1.5
plus
0.25
times 9.8
and so this is going to be
39.95 newtons
so that's the tension force at the
bottom it's greater than
what it is on top
now let's calculate the tension force
at the middle of the circle
so what you need to know is that the
middle of the circle if it's moving fast
enough
the tension force is approximately equal
to the centripetal force
so it's going to be about 0.25
times 15 meters per second
squared
divided by the radius of 1.5
and so that's about
37.5 newtons
at the center
so that's an approximation
but if it's not moving fast enough
the answer will
vary a little
so at the center
the rope is not going to be exactly
horizontal
it's going to be at a slight angle
and so that's the tension force
this is t x
and this is t y
now usually t y is going to be a lot
smaller than t x
at the center of the circle
and here's mg
so to get the tension force
as we said before it's going to be t x
squared plus t y squared
and we know t ax is equal to the
centripetal force
mv squared over r
and t y
is equal to the weight force
so that's going to be mg and then square
so let's plug this in
now we already know what mv squared over
r is
based on the last answer
that was 37.5
and the weight mg that's
0.25 times 9.8
which is 2.45
as you can see 2.45 is relatively small
compared to 37.5
so t is going to be about this answer
this is not going to change much but
we'll go ahead and do it for the sake of
seeing it
so if you type this in your calculator
the exact tension force is 37.58
so it changes a little but for the most
part
it's about the same
you